<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2 on Earth System Evolution</title>
    <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication_types/2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2 on Earth System Evolution</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication_types/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Eurasian ice sheet collapse was a major source of Meltwater Pulse 1A 14,600 years ago</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/brendryen_et_al_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/brendryen_et_al_2020/</guid>
      <description>We show that marine-based sectors of the Eurasian ice sheet complex collapsed at the Bølling transition and contributed significantly to Meltwater Pulse 1a.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A robust calibration of the clumped isotopes to temperature relationship for foraminifers</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/meinicke_et_al_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/meinicke_et_al_2020/</guid>
      <description> Supplementary notes can be added here, including code and math.   -- </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UncertainData.jl: a Julia package for working with measurements and datasets with uncertainties</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_2019/</guid>
      <description>UncertainData.jl provides an interface to represent data with associated uncertainties for the Julia programming language, using a resampling approach to deal with uncertainties in calculations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Was Common Era glacier expansion in the Arctic Atlantic region triggered by unforced atmospheric cooling?</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/vanderbilt_et_al_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/vanderbilt_et_al_2019/</guid>
      <description> Supplementary notes can be added here, including code and math.   -- </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jurassic shift from abiotic to biotic control on marine ecological success</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/eichenseer_et_al_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/eichenseer_et_al_2019/</guid>
      <description>Secular changes of ocean chemistry and temperature governs the ecological success of aragonitic calcifiers from the Ordovician to the Middle Jurassic, but not thereafter. This regime shift coincides with the proliferation of calcareous plankton in the mid-Mesozoic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nitrifier abundance and diversity peak at deep redox transition zones</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/zhao_et_al_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/zhao_et_al_2019/</guid>
      <description>We provide quantitative constraints on microbial nitrogen cycling in open ocean oligotrophic sediments from seafloor to basement. Local peaks in diversity and abundance at redox transition zones deep within the sediments suggest that nitrogen cycling microbes are revived from their maintenance state and start growing again after millions of years of attrition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Application of Clumped Isotope Thermometry to Benthic Foraminifera</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/piasecki_et_al_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/piasecki_et_al_2019/</guid>
      <description> Supplementary notes can be added here, including code and math.   -- </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transfer entropy computation using the Perron-Frobenius operator</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/diego_et_al_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/diego_et_al_2019/</guid>
      <description>We compute transfer entropy by estimating the invariant measure from the invariant distribution of the transfer operator approximated from time series. We use two methods for approximating the transfer operator, and find that our methods are robust to noise and show promising performance relative to other transfer entropy estimators.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evidence of early deglaciation (18 000 cal a BP) and a postglacial relative sea‐level curve from southern Karmøy, south‐west Norway</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/vasskog_et_al_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/vasskog_et_al_2019/</guid>
      <description> Supplementary notes can be added here, including code and math.   -- </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forcing of Late Pleistocene ice volume by spatially variable summer energy</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_et_al_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_et_al_2018/</guid>
      <description>We leverage the intrinsic dynamical information in empirical records to show that the external forcing of ice volume encompasses insolation signals with a wide range of orbital frequency content, and cannot be fully accounted for by a unique time series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Causality from palaeontological time series</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_liow_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_liow_2018/</guid>
      <description>We review some of the ways in which causal connections can be extracted from palaeontological time series and provide an overview of three recently developed analytical frameworks that have been applied to palaeontological questions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On formation-based sampling proxies and why they should not be used to correct the fossil record</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/dunhill_et_al_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/dunhill_et_al_2018/</guid>
      <description>We show that using formation counts as a sampling proxy to correct the fossil record via residual modelling is ill founded.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common species link global ecosystems to climate change: dynamical evidence in the planktonic fossil record</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_et_al_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_et_al_2017/</guid>
      <description>We use common and widespread species of planktonic foraminifera in deep-sea sediments and show that the observed global occupancy of planktonic foraminifera has been dynamically coupled to past oceanographic changes captured in deep-ocean temperature reconstructions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disentangling rock record bias and common-cause from redundancy in the British fossil record</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/dunhill_et_al_2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/dunhill_et_al_2014/</guid>
      <description>We show that outcrop area contains a signal useful for predicting changes in fossil richness as well as collection and formation counts, whilst the latter two are information redundant with fossil richness. Our results suggest that the widespread use of collection and formation counts to correct the raw richness data may be unwarranted.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Long‐term evolutionary and ecological responses of calcifying phytoplankton to changes in atmospheric CO2</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_et_al_2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_et_al_2012/</guid>
      <description>We show that coccolithophores were globally more common and widespread, larger, and more heavily calcified in the pre‐34 Ma greenhouse world, and declined along with pCO$&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; during the Oligocene (34–23 Ma). Our results suggest that atmospheric pCO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; has exerted an important long‐term control on coccolithophores.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Correlating microbial community profiles with geochemical data in highly stratified sediments from the Arctic Mid-Ocean Ridge</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/jorgensen_et_al_2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/jorgensen_et_al_2012/</guid>
      <description>We show a significant statistical relationship between variation in geochemical composition and prokaryotic community structure within deep-sea sediments near the hydrothermal vent field Loki’s Castle at the Arctic Mid-Ocean Ridge, in the Norwegian-Greenland Sea.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detecting common-cause relationships with directional information transfer</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_2011_lyell/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_2011_lyell/</guid>
      <description>I show how quantifying directional information transfer between variables can correctly distinguish a common-cause variable from a spurious relationship, even in cases where correlations are misleading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phanerozoic Earth system evolution and marine biodiversity</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_peters_2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_peters_2011/</guid>
      <description>We show that Phanerozoic records of seawater chemistry and continental flooding contain information on the diversity of marine animals that is independent of sedimentary rock quantity and sampling. Linkages between biodiversity and environmental records likely reflect complex biotic responses to changing ocean redox conditions and long-term sea-level fluctuations driven by plate tectonics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-parametric inference of causal interactions from geological records</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_2011_ajs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_2011_ajs/</guid>
      <description>A non-parametric estimate of information transfer (IT) is used to quantify (1) the relative strength of statistical dependence among three variables, including nonlinear relationships, and (2) the directionality of coupling between two variables, compared to surrogate time series.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>