<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Haaga KA on Earth System Evolution</title>
    <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/authors/haaga-ka/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Haaga KA on Earth System Evolution</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 00:00:01 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/authors/haaga-ka/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A simple test for causality in complex systems</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_et_al_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 00:00:01 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_et_al_2020/</guid>
      <description>We show that the evolution of any dynamical system is related to a predictive asymmetry that quantifies causal connections from limited observations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eurasian ice sheet collapse was a major source of Meltwater Pulse 1A 14,600 years ago</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/brendryen_et_al_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/brendryen_et_al_2020/</guid>
      <description>We show that marine-based sectors of the Eurasian ice sheet complex collapsed at the Bølling transition and contributed significantly to Meltwater Pulse 1a.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UncertainData.jl: a Julia package for working with measurements and datasets with uncertainties</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_2019/</guid>
      <description>UncertainData.jl provides an interface to represent data with associated uncertainties for the Julia programming language, using a resampling approach to deal with uncertainties in calculations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Was Common Era glacier expansion in the Arctic Atlantic region triggered by unforced atmospheric cooling?</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/vanderbilt_et_al_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/vanderbilt_et_al_2019/</guid>
      <description> Supplementary notes can be added here, including code and math.   -- </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jurassic shift from abiotic to biotic control on marine ecological success</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/eichenseer_et_al_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/eichenseer_et_al_2019/</guid>
      <description>Secular changes of ocean chemistry and temperature governs the ecological success of aragonitic calcifiers from the Ordovician to the Middle Jurassic, but not thereafter. This regime shift coincides with the proliferation of calcareous plankton in the mid-Mesozoic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transfer entropy computation using the Perron-Frobenius operator</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/diego_et_al_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/diego_et_al_2019/</guid>
      <description>We compute transfer entropy by estimating the invariant measure from the invariant distribution of the transfer operator approximated from time series. We use two methods for approximating the transfer operator, and find that our methods are robust to noise and show promising performance relative to other transfer entropy estimators.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evidence of early deglaciation (18 000 cal a BP) and a postglacial relative sea‐level curve from southern Karmøy, south‐west Norway</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/vasskog_et_al_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/vasskog_et_al_2019/</guid>
      <description> Supplementary notes can be added here, including code and math.   -- </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamically invariant surrogate data generation using the Perron-Frobenius (transfer) operator</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_et_al_surrogates/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_et_al_surrogates/</guid>
      <description>We present two new methods for generating uni- and multivariate surrogate data derived from transfer operator approximation. We demonstrate how these surrogates can be used to produce more reliable statistics for the underlying dynamics, such as attractor dimension estimates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forcing of Late Pleistocene ice volume by spatially variable summer energy</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_et_al_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_et_al_2018/</guid>
      <description>We leverage the intrinsic dynamical information in empirical records to show that the external forcing of ice volume encompasses insolation signals with a wide range of orbital frequency content, and cannot be fully accounted for by a unique time series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common species link global ecosystems to climate change: dynamical evidence in the planktonic fossil record</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_et_al_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_et_al_2017/</guid>
      <description>We use common and widespread species of planktonic foraminifera in deep-sea sediments and show that the observed global occupancy of planktonic foraminifera has been dynamically coupled to past oceanographic changes captured in deep-ocean temperature reconstructions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>