<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Diego D on Earth System Evolution</title>
    <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/authors/diego-d/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Diego D on Earth System Evolution</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 00:00:01 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/authors/diego-d/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A simple test for causality in complex systems</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_et_al_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 00:00:01 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_et_al_2020/</guid>
      <description>We show that the evolution of any dynamical system is related to a predictive asymmetry that quantifies causal connections from limited observations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transfer entropy computation using the Perron-Frobenius operator</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/diego_et_al_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/diego_et_al_2019/</guid>
      <description>We compute transfer entropy by estimating the invariant measure from the invariant distribution of the transfer operator approximated from time series. We use two methods for approximating the transfer operator, and find that our methods are robust to noise and show promising performance relative to other transfer entropy estimators.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamically invariant surrogate data generation using the Perron-Frobenius (transfer) operator</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_et_al_surrogates/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_et_al_surrogates/</guid>
      <description>We present two new methods for generating uni- and multivariate surrogate data derived from transfer operator approximation. We demonstrate how these surrogates can be used to produce more reliable statistics for the underlying dynamics, such as attractor dimension estimates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forcing of Late Pleistocene ice volume by spatially variable summer energy</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_et_al_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/haaga_et_al_2018/</guid>
      <description>We leverage the intrinsic dynamical information in empirical records to show that the external forcing of ice volume encompasses insolation signals with a wide range of orbital frequency content, and cannot be fully accounted for by a unique time series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common species link global ecosystems to climate change: dynamical evidence in the planktonic fossil record</title>
      <link>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_et_al_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.earthsystemevolution.com/publication/hannisdal_et_al_2017/</guid>
      <description>We use common and widespread species of planktonic foraminifera in deep-sea sediments and show that the observed global occupancy of planktonic foraminifera has been dynamically coupled to past oceanographic changes captured in deep-ocean temperature reconstructions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>