<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Earth System Evolution</title>
    <link>/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Earth System Evolution</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Forcing of Late Pleistocene ice volume by spatially variable summer energy</title>
      <link>/publication/haaga_et_al_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/haaga_et_al_2017/</guid>
      <description>Insolation, or the amount of solar radiation reaching the Earth, varies across latitudes, and its importance as a dynamical forcing of global climate is debated. Here we use the intrinsic dynamical information in global sea level reconstructions to show that integrated summer insolation at different latitudes was a significant forcing of global ice volume during the past 800,000 years. Using a model-free approach, we provide an explicit test of the conventional assumption that Northern Hemisphere summer insolation represents the external forcing of the climate system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On formation-based sampling proxies and why they should not be used to correct the fossil record</title>
      <link>/publication/dunhill_hannisdal_brocklehurst_benton_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/dunhill_hannisdal_brocklehurst_benton_2017/</guid>
      <description>The paper can be found here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Source-to-sink analysis in an active extensional setting: Holocene erosion and deposition in the Sperchios rift, central Greece</title>
      <link>/publication/pechlivanidou_et_al_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/pechlivanidou_et_al_2017/</guid>
      <description>The paper can be found here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common species link global ecosystems to climate change: dynamical evidence in the planktonic fossil record</title>
      <link>/publication/hannisdal_haaga_reitan_diego_liow_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/hannisdal_haaga_reitan_diego_liow_2017/</guid>
      <description>Common species shape the world around us, and changes in their commonness signify large-scale shifts in ecosystem structure and function. However, our understanding of long-term ecosystem response to environmental forcing in the deep past is centred on species richness, neglecting the disproportional impact of common species. Here, we use common and widespread species of planktonic foraminifera in deep-sea sediments to track changes in observed global occupancy (proportion of sampled sites at which a species is present and observed) through the turbulent climatic history of the last 65 Myr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ocean-Ice Sheet Interactions in the Norwegian Sea and Teleconnections to Low Latitude Hydrology and Atmospheric Circulation</title>
      <link>/publication/brendryen_hannisdal_haaga_et_al_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/brendryen_hannisdal_haaga_et_al_2016/</guid>
      <description>Some short description of the talk (or abstract?)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-parametric causal assessment in deep-time geological records</title>
      <link>/publication/haaga_et_al_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/haaga_et_al_2016/</guid>
      <description>The abstract is published here, and is available as a pdf file. The presentation is also available as a Shiny application.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disentangling rock record bias and common-cause from redundancy in the British fossil record</title>
      <link>/publication/dunhill_hannisdal_benton_2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/dunhill_hannisdal_benton_2014/</guid>
      <description>The paper can be found here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Long‐term evolutionary and ecological responses of calcifying phytoplankton to changes in atmospheric CO2</title>
      <link>/publication/hannisdal_hendericks_liow_2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/hannisdal_hendericks_liow_2012/</guid>
      <description>The paper is available as a pdf file, along with the supplementary materials.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Correlating microbial community proﬁles with geochemical data in highly stratiﬁed sediments from the Arctic Mid-Ocean Ridge </title>
      <link>/publication/jorgensen_hannisdal_et_al_2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/jorgensen_hannisdal_et_al_2012/</guid>
      <description>The paper, including supplementary materials, is available as a pdf. Andreas P. Teske also published a commentary on the paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detecting common-cause relationships with directional information transfer</title>
      <link>/publication/hannisdal_2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/hannisdal_2011/</guid>
      <description>The paper is available as a pdf file.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phanerozoic Earth system evolution and marine biodiversity</title>
      <link>/publication/hannisdal_peters_2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/hannisdal_peters_2011/</guid>
      <description>The Phanerozoic fossil record of marine animal diversity covaries with the amount of marine sedimentary rock. The extent to which this covariation reflects a geologically controlled sampling bias remains unknown. We show that Phanerozoic records of seawater chemistry and continental flooding contain information on the diversity of marine animals that is independent of sedimentary rock quantity and sampling. Interrelationships among variables suggest long-term interactions among continental flooding, sulfur and carbon cycling, and macroevolution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-parametric inference of causal interactions from geological records</title>
      <link>/publication/hannisdal_2011b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/hannisdal_2011b/</guid>
      <description>The paper is available as a pdf file.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the relationship between macrostratigraphy and geological processes: quantitative information capture and sampling robustness</title>
      <link>/publication/hannisdal_peters_2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/hannisdal_peters_2010/</guid>
      <description>The paper is available as a pdf file.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>